# Alicia Savelli

☑ aliciasavelli@gmail.com • ② aliciasavelli.github.io

I am an undergraduate student going into my final year of a physics degree at Brock University with previous Bachelor's degrees in mathematics and education. I am extremely passionate about astronomy, physics, mathematics, research, and teaching, and have significant experience and skills to support me in a career in science. I am interested in the fields of cosmology, galaxy formation and evolution, and relativity.

### Education

| Brock | Univ | ersity |
|-------|------|--------|
|       |      |        |

2020 - 2022B.Sc. Physics (Honours)

- 92% average in upper level courses (4.0 GPA on 4 point scale)
- 89% cumulative average (4.0 GPA on 4 point scale)
- Top 15% of faculty

## **Brock University**

B.Sc. Mathematics (Honours), minor in Physics

2014 - 2019

- 93% average in upper level courses (4.0 GPA on 4 point scale)
- 88% cumulative average (4.0 GPA on 4 point scale)
- Top 15% of faculty

#### **Brock University**

2014 - 2019B.Ed.

- Intermediate/Senior qualifications
- Straight P1s(As) 94% cumulative average (4.0 GPA on 4 point scale)

#### Notre Dame Catholic Secondary School

OSSD 2010 - 2014

- Ontario Scholar with 90% average in top six grade 12 courses

## Research Experience

## Undergraduate Thesis.....

## **Exploring the Possibility of Faster-than-Light Travel in Our Universe** Supervisor: Prof. Barak Shoshany

**Brock University** 

2020 - 2021

- Using Mathematica and General Relativity to investigate the possibility of Faster-than-Light travel
- Extending the Alcubierre and Natario Warpdrive metrics to 5 spacetime dimensions
- Proposal, midterm, and final presentations to Faculty and interested public along with written thesis submission

#### Research Projects.

## Analogues of the Milky Way in Cosmological Simulations

**University of Toronto** 

Supervisors: Dr. Ted Mackereth & Dr. Josh Speagle

Summer 2021

 Used Python and data from the EAGLE suite of cosmological simulations to identify and analyze Milky Way Analogues (MWAs)

- Determined a "Milky Way-ness" parameter and studied its effect on various properties of the MWAs both at present-day and throughout their formation histories
- Midterm and final presentations, academic poster, and research summary delivered to Faculty and interested public

Galactic Archaeology using Milky Way Survey Data and Simulations Supervisors: Dr. Ted Mackereth & Dr. Josh Speagle

**University of Toronto** *Winter & Summer 2022* 

## **Publications**

### Exploring the Possibility of Faster-than-Light Travel in Our Universe

Alicia Savelli, Barak Shoshany

In prep.

## Scholarships, Awards & Honours

## Summer Undergraduate Research Program (SURP) Fellowship

Canadian Institute for Theoretical Astrophysics; Dunlap Institute for Astronomy & Astrophysics, \$9,595

2021

## **SURP Student Spotlight**

Canadian Institute for Theoretical Astrophysics; Dunlap Institute for Astronomy & Astrophysics

2021

## **SURP Poster Contest – Runner Up**

Canadian Institute for Theoretical Astrophysics; Dunlap Institute for Astronomy & Astrophysics

2021

#### Dean's Honour List

Brock University

2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2021

- Awarded to students with an 80% average or greater each academic year
- Received every year of B.Sc. (Math) & B.Sc. (Physics) degrees
- Additional distinction of top 15% of the faculty

## **Brock Scholars Award**

Brock University, \$8,000

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

- Entrance scholarship for incoming averages of 90% or greater
- \$2,000/year for a maximum of 4 years, renewed if average is maintained at 80% or greater

#### Ontario Scholar

Halton Catholic District School Board

2014

- Distinction for graduating students with an average of 79.5% or greater in top six grade 12 courses

#### Top Hat Marching Orchestra Scholarship

Top Hat Marching Orchestra, \$1,000

2014

#### French Second Language Award

Halton Catholic District School Board, \$50

2014

- Awarded to graduating student with the highest mark in a grade 12 French course

## **Conference Talks**

## SDSS-V 2021 Collaboration Meeting

Johns Hopkins University/Online

Analogues of the Milky Way in Cosmological Simulations

August 2021

## **Conference Posters**

## SDSS-V 2021 Collaboration Meeting

Wembley High Technology College

Johns Hopkins University/Online

Analogues of the Milky Way in Cosmological Simulations

August 2021

## **Teaching Experience**

## Secondary Teacher

London, UK

Secondary Maths Teacher

September 2019 – July 2020

- Taught five maths classes from the GCSE Foundation and Higher curricula to Key Stage 3 and Key stage 4 learners at various levels of academic achievement
- Developed and delivered engaging and differentiated lessons, managed classroom behaviour, regularly assigned and marked homework
  - Year 9 form tutor
- Volunteered to participate in and organize extra curricular activities such as a tutoring club, a puzzles club, a maths news letter, and UKMT national maths challenges

# St. John Henry Newman Catholic Secondary School (HWCDSB) Physics Student Teacher

Stoney Creek, ON

March – May 2019

- B.Ed. Practicum
- Taught one SPH3U grade 11 universy level physics class and two SPH4U grade 12 university level physics classes
- Entirely responsible for creating notes and lessons that delivered the curriculum, and developing and marking tests, quizzes, assignments, and lab experiments/reports
- Volunteered with the school's concert band and lunchtime and after-school tutoring/homework clubs

#### Cathedral High School (HWCDSB)

Hamilton, ON

Math Student Teacher

 $November-December\ 2018$ 

- B.Ed. Practicum
- Taught one MPM1D grade 9 academic level math class and one MCR3U grade 11 university level math class
- Entirely responsible for creating notes and lessons that delivered the curriculum, and developing and marking tests, quizzes, and assignments
  - Volunteered with the after-school homework club

## Primary Teacher

## Prince of Wales South Public School (NDSB)

Thorold, ON

Student Teacher

October 2015 - March 2016

- B.Ed. Practicum
- Delivered Levelled Literacy Intevervention (LLI) program
- Helped students of all ages advance their reading levels in small groups of three to four students

## Professional Primary, Secondary, & Post-Secondary Tutor.....

#### Oxford Learning Centres Inc.

**Burlington & Stoney Creek, ON** 

Teacher

May 2017 – Present

- Tutor in groups of one to three high school students, and occasionally students at the college or primary levels
  - Specialize in intermediate and senior level math, calculus, data management, and physics, but

also tutor students in chemistry, general science, English, French, and more

#### **Private Tutor**

Independent Private Tutor

2014 - Present

- One-on-one private tutoring in all levels and categories of secondary math and science and first-year math and physics

Other

## **Education Quality and Accountability Office**

Etobicoke, ON

July 2019

2015-2016

Score

- Scored academic- and applied-level grade 9 math EQAO tests

## **Brock University Mathematics Department**

St. Catharines, ON

Exam Proctor

- Proctored first-year math midterms and final exams

**Other Relevant Work Experience** 

McDonalds Canada Burlington, ON

Team Leader, Crew

2013 – 2019

- Responsibilities included area and shift management, customer service, order taking & filling, and birthday parties

 Transferable skills to research and education include strong leadership & team management, collaboration, time management, stress management, organization, and communication

ArcelorMittal Dofasco Hamilton, ON
Data Analyst Summer 2018

 Developed and enhanced queries and data reports to improve company efficiency, wrote macros to supplement reports

Enhanced technical skills with Visual Basic, SQL, MS Excel, and MS Access

## Workshops, Training, & Professional Development

## Introduction to Python

Student May 2021

- 2-week intensive introductory course to coding and data analysis with Python

- Covered topics such as advanced plotting, statistical analysis, and machine learning

## **SURP Astro 101 Lecture Series**

**University of Toronto** 

**University of Toronto** 

Summer Research Student

Summer 2021

- Summer series of weekly introductory astronomy lectures
- Topics covered included planets & exoplanets, galaxy formation & evolution, instrumentation, statistics, cosmology, and black holes

## **SURP Professional Development Series**

**University of Toronto** 

Summer Research Student

Summer 2021

- Summer series of weekly professional development workshops and seminars
- Topics covered included careers in astronomy, grad school applications and experiences, and presenting research

Shutdown STEM
Attendee

University of Toronto

July 2021

- Day-long workshop within the Astronomy & Astrophysics department pertaining to action

against racism with a special focus on Indigenous peoples

- Workshop included presentations, discussions, and activities such as researching and letterwriting

#### **SAFETALK Mental Health Training**

**Brock University** 

March 2018

- Training in speaking to young people about their mental health and the best ways to be available and offer support
  - Awarded certificate

## **Relevant Coursework**

- o Astronomy: Introduction to Astronomy, Planetary Science
- Physics: Classical Mechanics, Electromagnetism, Quantum Mechanics, Statstical Mechanics & Thermal Physics, Optics, Special & General Relativity, Experimental Physics
- Mathematics: Calculus, Vector Calculus, Differential Equations, Linear Algebra, Statistics, Mathematical Physics, Differential Geometry
- **Computer Programming:** Mathematics Integrated with Computers and Applications I/II/III, Introduction to Scientific Computing
- o Education: Mathematics, Physics, Diversity, Special Education

## **Technical & Personal Skills**

- o Programming Languages: Python, Visual Basic, SQL, Physica, Extrema
- o **Software:** Maple, Mathematica, LATEX, Git
- o Operating Systems: Windows, Linux
- o Professional Skills: Presenting, writing, teaching
- **Personal Skills:** Enthusiasm, organization, communication, time management, leadership, collaboration, perseverance, diligence

## **Professional Memberships**

**Ontario College of Teachers (OCT)** 

Member ID: 698209

2019 – Present

## **Extracurricular Activities**

**Burlington Concert Band** 

Burlington, ON 2018-2019

**Brock University Winds Ensemble** 

St. Catharines, ON

 $2^{nd}$  Clarinet

1st Clarinet

2014-2018

**Brock Intramural Sports** 

Brock University

Soccer, Baseball, Volleyball

2016-2018

# Media Appearances

| SURP Project Showcase <u>Poster</u> , Research Summary  | 2021 |
|---|------|
| SURP Student Spotlight Student of the Week interview  | 2021 |
| A university mathematics department's adoption of constructionist math courses MICA Project interview | 2017 |